<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A secular sermon concerning the doctrine of the Gospell by the goodnes and power of God restored in the fifteenth age from the birth of our Lord Iesus Christ. Made by the reuerend and worthy precher Mr. Abraham Scultetus, in the High-dutch tongue. After by another translated into Latin, and now out of Latin into English</title>
            <author>Scultetus, Abraham, 1566-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106166</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841889</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841889</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6504</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11824)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6504)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1334:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A secular sermon concerning the doctrine of the Gospell by the goodnes and power of God restored in the fifteenth age from the birth of our Lord Iesus Christ. Made by the reuerend and worthy precher Mr. Abraham Scultetus, in the High-dutch tongue. After by another translated into Latin, and now out of Latin into English</title>
                  <author>Scultetus, Abraham, 1566-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>41, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones, dwelling in Red-crosse streete neare S. Giles Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno 1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, of the Latin translation by Christian Kyfert, of an untraced work.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through, and some leaves cropped at head; beginning-page 17 from Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.) Library copy spliced at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, German --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6504:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:6504:1"/>
A SECVLAR SERMON CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING THE DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpell by the goodnes and power of God reſtored in the fifteenth <hi>age from the birth of our Lord</hi> Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>MADE BY THE REVEREND AND WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Preacher M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>ABRAHAM SCVLTETVS,</hi> in the High-dutch tongue.</p>
            <p>AFTER BY ANOTHER TRANSLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Latin, and now out of Latin into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Iones,</hi> dwelling in Red-croſſe ſtreete neare S. Giles Church, Anno 1618.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6504:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:6504:2"/>
            <head>A SECVLAR SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON MADE IN THE Arch-Palatine court, in the yeare 1617. And of <hi>Ianuary</hi> the firſt. <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Seculum</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>tin, ſignifieth <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> age, contain<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> an hundered yeares. There<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> this Sermon <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> called ſecular <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>cauſe it cont<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>neth the ſtory <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the laſt hun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> yeares, whe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Goſpell <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſtored, from <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> yeare <hi>1517,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> this yeare <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which is written by the Kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> wee ſee <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 145.</note> certainely helpeth at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. <hi>The mercy of God is ouer all his workes.</hi> For, from this mercy wee doe freely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that wee haue receiued this benefit, that we liue, and in good health begin this new yeare. From this mercy it is, that being free from peſtilence, and death, wee haue not ſeene bloody warres, nor other publicke ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities. From the ſame mercy we haue receiued it, that by the celebration of the Natiuitie of Chriſt, (which we haue heere liberty ſolemnly to keepe) we ioyfully vnderſtand, how, for our good, Chriſt was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6504:3"/>
borne at <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> how the Angels ſweetely deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs with their hymnes, how the ſhepheards of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> daunced, with a holy ioy; and how <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Anna</hi> entertained with kiſſes the Sauiour newly borne.</p>
            <p>Goe too then, O <hi>Palatinate,</hi> magnifie the Lord thy God with due praiſes: and thou O <hi>Heidle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> with pious affection, publiſh his name and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is moſt worthy to bee worſhipped and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned.</p>
            <p>And becauſe now this is the hundred yeere, ſince which time the euerlaſting and Almightie God, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon our Aunceſtors with the eye of his grace and fauour, deliuered them out of the horrible dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Popery, and brought them into the cleare and faire light of the Goſpell, let vs alſo looking backe to theſe times, behold and conſider, how graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, God hath declared himſelfe to his Church in the ſaide hundred yeares, and how mercifully hee hath gathered it together, hauing beene before diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed and ſcattered heere and there, and being ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, how wonderfully hee hath preſerued it, vnto this preſent time.</p>
            <p n="2">2 For ſo it will be made manifeſt, that the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, doeth worthily and agreeably to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, beare the name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> (that is a <hi>Sauiour)</hi> that was giuen at his Circumciſion, expreſſing it by really ſauing his people, and to be our true Ieſus and Sauiour, not onely by the excellency of his merit, but alſo by the vertue and power of his effectuall operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and working which he ſheweth out moſt mightily in, and towards his Church, and people.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:6504:3"/>
Moreouer alſo (as I perſwade my ſelfe) here will be matter and occaſion aboundantly miniſtred vnto vs, for the celebration and praiſe of the name of God, where we ſhall behold his wiſedome, omnipotency, goodnes and iuſtice, euery where moſt clearly ſhining in his gouernment of the Church in this century, or laſt hundred yeeres.</p>
            <p>And that I may ſhortly comprehend all this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: euen as God in times paſt reformed the world by the Apoſtles and their faithfull ſucceſſors: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the fifteenth hundred yeere from the birth of Chriſt, God I ſay began to order the reformation and gouernment of his Church? All which things my purpoſe is at this preſent, euidently to ſhewe and demonſtrate vnto you.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Whereas it behoued that Chriſt ſhould be borne one thouſand ſixe hundred and ſeuenteene yeeres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone: God ſent <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> as a forerunner, that hee might prepare and make ready a way for the Lord: In like ſort when the ſame Chriſt was (as it were) to bee borne againe, it pleaſed God that diuers preparatory helpes and furtherances to the reſt that was to follow ſhould be furniſhed, before he tooke in hand the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation it ſelfe of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Amongſt which meanes of preparing way to the ſaide reformation, moſt worthily I may name and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count firſt the liberall arts and ſciences, and the daily exerciſes of good ſciences, and chiefely of the three learned tongues and languages, as inſtruments to make way to the reformation that was to follow. In the next place I nominate and ranke Vniuerſities and particular Schooles (as they call them) which by a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6504:4"/>
commendable purpoſe and worthy example for imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and following, were in that time, partly foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and erected, and partly alſo preſerued and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged. To theſe I adde alſo the inuention of the Art of Printing, which before had ben vtterly vnknowne, and by meanes whereof it came to paſſe that Doctor <hi>Luthers</hi> bookes, being diſperſed and ſpread into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and moſt large countries and nations, came into very many mens hands, and were euery where read and diligently ſtudied. Here alſo amongſt the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide meanes, the tranſlation of the Scriptures is not to be paſſed by, but attentiuely to be conſidered. For in the yeere, one thouſand fiue hundred and fifteene, the olde Teſtament ſawe the light that was to bee wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for, being publiſhed in print in the originall He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew tongue by <hi>Frauncis Ximenius,</hi> being Arch-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> and a Cardinall: and ſo likewiſe was the new Teſtament printed in the yeere next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>Which bookes opened the eies of many, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelouſly raiſed their deſire, ſo that being inflamed with a zeale diligently to knowe and ſearch out the heauenly trueth, they might eaſily diſcerne, how far the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> had departed from the puritie of the Scripture.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In time paſt alſo, when Chriſt went about the reformation of the world, hee called not to that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice the Scribes and Phariſees which were of great authoritie, but hee choſe vnto it twelue Diſciples, men deſpiſed by the world, and eſteemed baſe, which for the moſt part were fiſher-men.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe one hundred yeeres agone, Chriſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6504:4"/>
in hand the worke of a new reformation, vſed not thereunto any purple-cloathed Praelate, nor Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, whoſe names were moſt floriſhing and famous, but he raiſed vp hereunto for this ſeruice <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> a Monke of the order of the <hi>Auguſtinians, Phillip Melanchthon</hi> a profeſſor and reader of the Greeke tongue in the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> and two Prieſts of ſmall account, to wit, <hi>Huldrich Zwinglius,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Oecolampadius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Moreouer the doctrine of the Goſpell breaking out, (at the firſt publiſhing of it by the Apoſtles) with a diuine and moſt powerfull force, ſuddenly like the lightning enlightned the vniuerſall world, ſo as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the time of <hi>Irenaeus</hi> reported to haue bin taught by <hi>Polycarpus</hi> ſcholler to <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle, Chriſt came to be famouſly known by the nations and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, both of the Eaſt and Weſt parts of the world: euen ſo, when as one hundred yeeres agone, after that the Idolatry of the Papiſts running (as if they had beene mad or bewitched after the worſhip of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages) being diſcouered, the contrite and wounded hearts of men were led (as by the hand) from their confidence in their owne merits, to the precious ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the death of Chriſt, it is incredible to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, with how great celeritie and ſpeede, and with what great ſucceſſe, the puritie of true Religion pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into all countries. For it reſted not now onely in Cities; neither was it content to remaine amongſt the inferiour of the Nobilitie and gentry: but it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Courts euen of Kings and Emperours, and gat their allowance and approbation.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe you then (for proofe hereof) that we
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6504:5"/>
firſt viewe the Cities? Amongſt theſe, the firſt that flouriſhed and were famous for the praiſe of ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Goſpell, were theſe: <hi>Strausborough, Breme, Norinberge, Worms, Erford, Hoſlaria,</hi> and <hi>Embden</hi> of <hi>Frize-land.</hi> All theſe chearfully &amp; with ready mindes receiued, and entertained the trueth comming vnto them, in the very firſt beginning. Theſe alſo kindled by &amp; by a ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t zeale of Religion in other countries. Amongſt theſe were <hi>Maydenborow, Hamborow, Lubeck, Brunſwick, Wiſmaria, Roſtochium,</hi> and almoſt all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Empire. Nay furthermore in <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>feland,</hi> the cities of <hi>Riga, Derbatum, Renalia,</hi> in <hi>Helu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tia</hi> or <hi>Switzer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Baſile, Scafhuſium, Tig<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum</hi> or <hi>Zurich, Berne,</hi> and diuers others. All which Cities as they embraced the doctrine of the Goſpell with great gladnes &amp; gratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, ſo <hi>Wolfgongus Capito</hi> hath left written a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar &amp; memorable act, in this reſpect, of the men of <hi>Berne,</hi> which is this: <hi>Hauing receiued the Goſpell,</hi> they ſet their priſoners at libertie, and proclaimed free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for ſuch as they had baniſhed out of the land, to returne into their Country againe, yeelding this notable reaſon for their ſo doing. For ſaid they, if we would haue diſmiſſed &amp; diſcharged our malefactors and priſoners in the honour of an earthly King, that ſhould haue come vnto vs. How much more now ought we then ſith Chriſt the King of glory is come vnto vs, bringing with him the moſt glorious bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of euerlaſting redemption? And therefore we moſt earneſtly wiſh and deſire that as much as might be, all men may be made partakers of ſo great a benefit and deliuerance as is now beſtowed vpon vs.</p>
            <p>In going out from the Cities, let vs view the degree
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6504:5"/>
of Knighthood. In this degree there attained a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Crowne of honour that noble <hi>Frauncis</hi> of <hi>Sic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kengen, Huldrick</hi> of <hi>Hutt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> and <hi>Silueſter</hi> of <hi>Schawen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi> For when <hi>Luther</hi> was miſerably vexed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by the Pope, they vndertooke the defending and protecting of him with al their force and power. And when <hi>Luther</hi> was excommunicated, and was thinking to flie into <hi>Bohemia</hi> for refuge, <hi>Schawenber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> before mentioned, offered him free acceſſe vnto him, and promiſed him a company of a hundred horſemen of <hi>Franconia</hi> to conduct him ſafely to him.</p>
            <p>Of this praiſe are alſo pertakers, the <hi>Landſhadii, Steinacenſes, Helmſtatenſes, Gemingenſes,</hi> and <hi>Menſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes,</hi> who euery one of them from the yeare 1521, and 1522, had procured the ſinceritie of the Goſpell to bee publickly preached in their territories. In whoſe ſteps, <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Salhauſen</hi> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> treading did the ſame, and being accuſed for it to <hi>Lewis</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> hee defended himſelfe with a notable Apology.</p>
            <p>Now amongſt the Princes that receiued the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, the heroicall worthies of the houſe of <hi>Saxonie</hi> obtained the principall place, to wit, <hi>Frederick</hi> the wiſe, <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſincere, and <hi>Iohn Frederick</hi> the conſtant, being Electors: whoſe moſt commendable example, euen ſtraightwayes from the beginning followed, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wis</hi> Count Palatine the Duke of <hi>Bipont, George Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> of <hi>Brandborow, Marques Albertus</hi> Duke of <hi>Pruſsia, Erneſtus</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> and <hi>Luneburg, Frauncis</hi> Duke of <hi>Luneburg, Phillip Landgraue</hi> of <hi>Haſsia, Wolf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gangus</hi> Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> and <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond, Duke of <hi>Sileſia, Lignicum,</hi> and <hi>Briga.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:6504:6"/>
From thence the fame of the Goſpell ſounding all abroad, there opned their gates alſo to the Lord Ieſus Chriſt in their countries, theſe Princes. <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Cleue,</hi> and his ſucceſſor <hi>William</hi> (although there fell <note place="margin">1533.</note> out ſome ſuch cauſes and times as ſuffered them not to finiſh and perfect the reformation which they had begun, ſo as it had beene to be wiſhed.</p>
            <p>Theſe princes alſo embraced the Goſpell, <hi>Hu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>drick</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1534.</note> Duke of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> with his brother <hi>George, Earle</hi> of <hi>Wirtemberg,</hi> and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nbelgard,</hi> and <hi>Bar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inus</hi> and <hi>Phillip</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1537.</note> Dukes of <hi>Pomerania, Ioachin</hi> the ſecond Elector of <note place="margin">1538.</note> 
               <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> &amp; his brother <hi>Iohn Seuerus, Henry</hi> Duke <note place="margin">1539.</note> of <hi>Saxonie</hi> father of <hi>Mourice</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus Electors,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1543.</note> 
               <hi>Hermannus</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Coullen, Charles Marques</hi> of <hi>Baden, Iulius</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke, Gotthardus</hi> Duke <note place="margin">1556.</note> 
               <note place="margin">1568.</note> of <hi>Curland, William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> to whom the lowcountrymen are much beholding in that reſpect.</p>
            <p>For what ſhould I ſpeake of the <hi>Arch-Palatine</hi> countrey? wherein wee haue the reformation made by the Electors, that is begun by <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond, <note place="margin">1546.</note> continued by <hi>Otto Henricus,</hi> and finiſhed &amp; brought to perfection by <hi>Frederick</hi> the third, to his eternall and greateſt honour, and our vnſpeakeable benefit and comfort. Neither was <hi>Lewis</hi> the peaceable Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor eſtranged from fauouring the Goſpel, ſeeing that <note place="margin">1538.</note> his brother <hi>Frederick</hi> graciouſly graunted free exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Religion of the Goſpell to eight cities ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in one precinct in the higher country of the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate, which are <hi>Amberg, Neufore, Kam, Nafurg, Wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Nanpurg, Au<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bac,</hi> and <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnate.</hi> Herein alſo it ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth moſt worthy to be remembred, that a Prince of the Empire <hi>George</hi> Earle of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> a Prince of moſt <note place="margin">1548.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:6504:6"/>
approued pietie and holineſſe, is ſaide to haue eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the doctrine of the Goſpell ſo precious, that hee doubted not himſelfe in his own perſon, out of a rare and extraordinary zeale to deliuer it to his ſubiects preaching vnto them. We haue heard alſo, that the ſame Prince gra<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with a mariage-Sermon, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and his noble wife, being publickely maried according to the accuſtomed right and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Church.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe the Queene of <hi>Denmarke</hi> ioyfully gratulating the ſpouſe her daughter, ſaide often, that no greater grace could happen to her in the world.</p>
            <p>After theſe Princes followed alſo Kings, euery of them in their ſeuerall times and diſtances of yeares. Amongſt theſe, the firſt was <hi>Frederick</hi> King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> who hauing ſhaken off the yoake of the Pope, embraced the pure doctrine of the word of God.</p>
            <p>Soone after followed him <hi>Guſtarus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden, Mary</hi> Queene of <hi>Hungary,</hi> ſiſter to the Emperour <hi>Charles, Marga<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et</hi> of <hi>Valoys,</hi> Queene of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Frauncis</hi> King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> to whom ſhee moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended often-times, the cauſe of ſuch Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians as being exiled, fled for refuge into <hi>Fraunce,</hi> yeelding her ſelfe moſt gratious vnto them, yea and as if ſhe had borne the kind affection of a mother to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them. Such a one was alſo <hi>Renata,</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth, King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> who hauing beene maried to <hi>Hercules</hi> Duke of <hi>Ferrary,</hi> enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the darkeneſſe of <hi>Italy</hi> it ſelfe with the light of the Goſpell. And when ſhee had returned widow and dowager into <hi>Fraunce,</hi> in the tempeſtuous and ſtormy time of the moſt foule and ſhamefull maſſacre, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6504:7"/>
ſlaughter extreamly raging in <hi>Paris,</hi> and euery where elſe in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> in the yeare 1572. ſhe reached forth a gratious and helpefull hand, for the reliefe of the moſt afflicted ſtate of many godly perſons: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others ſhee receiued and entertained that moſt religious and worthy teacher maiſter <hi>Daniel Toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanus,</hi> together with his wife and children, and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully patronized and defended him in the time of extreame danger.</p>
            <p>Now if wee behold and conſider the reformation of the Engliſh Churches, here commeth to my mind, and as a moſt beautifull and comfortable Starre ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, the moſt gratious King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who being inkindled with an heroicall Spirit and zeale, deſired thoſe Churches to bee throughly cleanſed from Popiſh Idolatry. After alſo, his ſiſter Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> followed his pietie and moſt reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious example both with like affection and ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>What? did not alſo <hi>Iames Hamelton</hi> Viceroy in <hi>Scotland,</hi> firſt permit and make free to euery one that would, the reading of the Bible in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tongue, and the order of prayer. By which worthy act, the true Chriſtian Religion ſtraightwaies tooke ſo great increaſe, as that the States in Parliament prouided by publicke lawe in the yeare 1561, that all the people ſhould liue quietly and in peace without reuiling, or iniurying one another for any pretence or excuſe of Religion.</p>
            <p>Moreouer this is alſo manifeſt by certaine proofes, that theſe three Emperours <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, <hi>Ferdinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> and <hi>Maximillian</hi> departed out of this life, reſting vpon the ſame comfort and faith, which <hi>Luther</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6504:7"/>
out of the Scriptures, preached and publiſhed, in that hee ſhewed and taught that all the hope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life conſiſteth in the death of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>After theſe notable perſonages of the ciuill ſtate, let vs now come alſo and remember the teachers of the Church: wherein we may conſider that after the Apoſtles time, God raiſed vp almoſt in a continuall ſucceſſion moſt worthy teachers, ſuch as theſe were, <hi>Ignatius, Policarpus, Iuſtinus</hi> Martyr, <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, Athenagoras, Origen, Cyprian, Tertullian, Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, Epiphanius, Hilarius, Baſil, Gregory</hi> of <hi>Nazianzene, Ierome, Auguſtine, Ambroſe, Chryſoſtome</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by whoſe worthy ſeruice &amp; labour, the worke of the Reformation of the world begun by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, was happily and with great ſucceſſe proceeded in, and furthered.</p>
            <p>And euen ſo to thoſe firſt goodly and glorious lights of the Church in Doctrine and Diuinitie, <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Melanchton, ZWinglius</hi> and <hi>Oecolampadius,</hi> God added &amp; adioyned other teachers, that were men fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for their pietie and learning, who receiuing the Goſpell from the former, as a lampe and a light deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vnto them (the fowleſt errors of Popery ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene diſcouered) haue brought with them a clearer and greater light of vnderſtanding and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the bookes of the Bible.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Helvetia</hi> and <hi>Switzerland,</hi> who is ignorant that there haue beene many, who partly by preaching, and partly by writing, haue ſerued the Church with great diligence and profit? Amongſt whom theſe men are worthy of immortall praiſe: <hi>Henry Bullinger, Rodolph Gualter, Oſwald Myconias, Conrade Pellicane,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:6504:8"/>
               <hi>Berthall Haller, Gaſper Megander, Leo Iuda, Benedict Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Iohn Wolfe, Lewis Lauater, Ioſias Simler, Bibliander, William Stuckius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe we demaund what teachers they haue had in high <hi>Germany?</hi> Surely in that countrey there hath beene great plenty of notable teachers. Such as were theſe, <hi>Ambroſe Blawrer, Iohn Swickius, Martin Bucer, Malthias Tellius, Wolfangus Capito, Caſpar Hedio, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Oſiander</hi> of <hi>Hala</hi> in <hi>Swevia, Erardus Schnepfius,</hi> and <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tin Frechtius</hi> at <hi>Tubinga, Ambroſe, Mollerus</hi> and <hi>Iohn Heſſe</hi> at <hi>Wratiſlavia</hi> or <hi>Breſla; Conrade, Somius</hi> at <hi>Vlms, Wolfangus Muſculns</hi> at <hi>Auguſta</hi> or <hi>Ausborow, Francis Lambert, Andrew H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>perias, Iohn Pincer, Denis Melander</hi> in <hi>Haſsia,</hi> and in <hi>Wittemberg Iaſper Cruciger</hi> both the father and the ſonne; <hi>Georg Maior, Iohn Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genhagius, Paul Eber, Iohn Foſter, Iohn Auenar, Henry Moller, Frederick Widebrame,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Pezelius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Livonia</hi> or <hi>Lief-land</hi> there haue beene worthy Preachers, as <hi>Andrew Cnophius</hi> and others, and in <hi>Boruſia, Iohn Poliander</hi> and <hi>Iohn Briſmana;</hi> in the lower <hi>Saxonie, Vrbanus Regius, Hermane Browne,</hi> and <hi>Albert Hardenbergius,</hi> in <hi>Friſia, Micronius, Menſo, Altingus,</hi> and diuers others.</p>
            <p>And who is there amongſt vs whom the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of theſe famous men doeth not moue and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with ſingular delight, to wit, of <hi>William Farell, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Viret, Iohn Caluin, Auſtin Marlorate, Theodore Beza, Antony Sadeel,</hi> and of <hi>Phillip Mor<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> of <hi>Pleſſay,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who partly by teaching, and partly by writing, haue mightily ouerthrowen Popery, and aduanced the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Neither hath this fauour of God beene wanting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6504:8"/>
vnto <hi>Spaine.</hi> For what men <hi>Spaine</hi> hath had teachers of the Euangelicall doctrine, the ſame it hath alſo moſt glorious Martyrs, to wit, <hi>Frauncis Drianda, Diazius,</hi> Doctor <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> Confeſſor to the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Italy</hi> it ſelfe alſo hath ſent vs ouer from thence moſt excellent Diuines to the very great benefite of our Churches, <hi>Peter Martyr, Ierom Zanchius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Immanuell Tremellius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe men alſo in <hi>Scotland,</hi> haue left vs moſt ample and large fruites of their ſeruice; for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <hi>Iohn Knoxe, Robert Rollock, Iohn Iohnſton,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others.</p>
            <p>But in England God hath ſet out, as vpon a Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſtage to be ſeene by all the world, very many famous and learned men, who haue ſtoutely defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and maintained the doctrine of the Goſpell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the deceitfull impoſtures of the Antichriſt of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſuch were theſe, <hi>Thomas Cranmer</hi> Arch biſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Hugh Latimer, Iohn Hooper, Nicholas Ridley, Iohn Rogers, Hugh Philpot, Iohn Iuell, Laurance Humphery,</hi> with <hi>William Whitaker, Iohn Rainolds, William Perkins, William Fulke,</hi> and an infinite number of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom it were too long to rehearſe.</p>
            <p>How ſhould I bee ſilent of the land of <hi>Denmarke</hi> which hath had moſt famous Preachers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, to wit, <hi>Palladius, Hemingius, Macabaeus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Hungarians</hi> alſo ſpeake of <hi>Michael Starinus</hi> as of their glory, who reformed many particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in it, and ſet Miniſters of the word ouer them, to whom hee himſelfe preſcribed what order was to bee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6504:9"/>
held for the making of Sermons profitable and fruit full, and in what maner the Sacraments were to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred. They will recite in like maner <hi>Steuen Szegeden, Paul Thurius, Iaſper Charles, Peter Melius, Martin Hollopaeus, Mathew Scaricaus, Thomas Fabricius</hi> of <hi>Tholna,</hi> and many others.</p>
            <p>And that I may mention no more, the Churches of <hi>Poland,</hi> euen to this day, not without a thankefull remembrance they ſpeake of that worthy noble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage <hi>Iohn Alaskaw,</hi> of the Earles of <hi>Gorkaw,</hi> and the Lords, <hi>Oſelinians,</hi> who in their time were a defence and an ornament to the doctrine of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>So doe they likewiſe ſpeake of thoſe notable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, <hi>Eraſmus Gliſner, Georg Iſraell, Iohn Laurence, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar Euchner, Iohn Turnorius,</hi> and others who haue fruitfully deliuered the Goſpell to the people.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Now to extend the compariſon begun yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the beginning God, who is moſt and onely wiſe, ſpread and propagated the Goſpell, by meanes which in appearance, were directly contrary to the furtherance of it: ſuch as was the ouerthrow of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and the diſperſion of Chriſts Diſciples into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers parts of the world. And the ſame courſe hath God obſerued euery wherein our time.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1522, that noble Gentleman <hi>Frauncis Sickingen</hi> had gathered ſo many worthy men into his Caſtle of <hi>Landſcale,</hi> as might ſeeme to haue beene ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to haue furniſhed ſome Vniuerſitie, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Schoole. For at one and the ſame time, hee had with him <hi>Iohn Oecolampadius, Martin Bucer, Iohn Schwebelius, Iaſpar Aquila.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, no long time after, when he was beſieged by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6504:9"/>
certaine Princes, he left it to the pleaſure of thoſe Diuines, to goe for their beſt ſafety and ſecuritie where euery one of them would.</p>
            <p>By which occaſion of that ſiege &amp; of their diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Iohn Schwebelius</hi> going to the <hi>Count-Palatine Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> Duke of <hi>Bi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ont,</hi> he laid there the firſt ſtone of the <hi>Euangelicall</hi> reformation. <hi>Martin Bucer</hi> went to <hi>Strawſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borowe,</hi> which with what fruit and benifit of the Church he did it, is manifeſt by the common voice and teſtimonie of all <hi>Germanie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Oecolampadius</hi> tooke his iorney to <hi>Baſile,</hi> to which Citie he ſo made knowen and apparent his learning and pietie, that he was invited and deſired with moſt earneſt requeſt to take paines to read and preach vnto them. Wherevnto after that he had yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in the ſpace of a few yeares, he ſo aduanced the cauſe of Religion, that the ſaid Citie greatly reioyced at the ſight of a full reformation, procured by him amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iaſper Aquila</hi> he went to <hi>Thuringia,</hi> and there fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered the edification of the Church of Chriſt, with great zeale, and happy ſucceſſe. A like occaſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt about the ſame time fel out at <hi>Treptqaine</hi> (a place in <hi>Pomerland)</hi> which was this. There floriſhed a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Colledge, that was famous by the learning of certaine men, of which Colledge, <hi>Iohn Bugenhagius</hi> was the Rector.</p>
            <p>Now it fell out, that <hi>Luthers</hi> booke of the <hi>Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> captiuitie being ſent from <hi>Lipſia,</hi> were deliuered there to <hi>Bugenhagius</hi> to be read ouer, who hauing ſlightly looked vpon it, is reported to haue ſaid to his fellowes, bretheren, the Sun did neuer ſee a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6504:10"/>
Heriticke then <hi>Luther.</hi> But after a few dayes loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king more diligently and attentiuely into the ſaid booke, he chaunged his opinion and teſtimony of him openly before the ſame bretheren, and ſaid: that all the world had bin drow<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed hitherto, in moſt palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errours. Which he a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>terwards ſet ſo clearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, as that they all conſented in iudgement with him. Which after that the Biſhop of <hi>Camintum</hi> came to the knowledge of, by and by (as the manner is) he began fiercely to perſecute them.</p>
            <p>Wherefore they began all to fly and prouide for the ſafety of their life. And <hi>Bugenhagius</hi> going to <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg,</hi> tooke an Eccleſiaſticall charge, and afterwards reformed the Churches of <hi>Hanborow</hi> and <hi>Lubeck,</hi> and of all the Kingdome of <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Andrew Cnophius</hi> went into <hi>Leif land,</hi> and there brought the Cittie of <hi>Riga</hi> to acknowledge and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the truth of the Goſpell, which at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning brake out into ſo great flames, that ſtraightwaies <hi>Darbetum</hi> and <hi>Reualia</hi> came thither (as it were) from the brightneſſe of it, to kindle their light.</p>
            <p>The reſt of them flying from <hi>Treptum,</hi> beſtowed themſelues abroad in the towne of <hi>Pomerland,</hi> and handled the cauſe of the Goſpell ſo happily &amp; with ſo great ſucceſſe as that by the authoritie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of <hi>Barnim</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> Dukes of <hi>Pomera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> the ſtates of the land being aſſembled together in that towne, by common councell and decree Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh abuſes were baniſhed out of all <hi>Pomerland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let vs view <hi>France</hi> and namely <hi>Meaux</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> there Biſhop <hi>Bricomet</hi> with great earneſtnes vndertooke to maintaine the cauſe of the Goſpell.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6504:10"/>
And hauing called together thether very many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, and amongſt them <hi>Iohn Faber Stapulenſis,</hi> a man of eminent and great name, he commanded them publickely to preach the true doctrine of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. But after when the Biſhop being terrified and put in feare, fell away from true religion, all the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters alſo were compelled to forſake the countrye: whereof ſome went into the Kingdome of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and ſome to <hi>Paris:</hi> and (althougth priuately and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret places) they inſtruct the people by their Sermons. Many of them alſo in the Citie of <hi>Metz,</hi> whither they had fled, began the building of that goodly Church, which euen to this day doth continue and flouriſhe. Others alſo we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to other places of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where they made Chriſt, and the doctrine of the Goſpell more famous.</p>
            <p>And is there any man, who herein may not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, admire, and publiſh the wiſedome of God? eſpecially, conſidering that he then ſheweth forth his mightie power for the helpe and aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Church, when we thinke it moſt of all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned and forſaken.</p>
            <p>The like thing hapned alſo in <hi>Italy,</hi> which (for the profeſſion of the Goſpell) baniſhed many godly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from <hi>Naples, Luca, Piſa</hi> and <hi>Locarne.</hi> All which perſecutions, the wiſedome of God directed to that ende, that by the ſeruice of the ſame men, which had beene baniſhed from theſe places, the building vp of the Churches in other countries, might be excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly raiſed vp. The ſame we know to haue beene done at <hi>Geneva, Zarick, London</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:6504:11"/>
In like maner, the ſmall <hi>Caldian</hi> warre being fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, the brethreen and profeſſors which were dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Morauia,</hi> came to <hi>Pole-land,</hi> where they who had beene refuſed by King <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> found a very gratious patron of <hi>Albert</hi> Duke of <hi>Boruſsia.</hi> Yet ſome of theſe turning backe againe into <hi>Polonia,</hi> were receiued by diuers noble men in <hi>Pole-land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what came of their returne? In the ſpace of eight yeares, there was ſo much effected by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry and labour, as that <hi>Peter Vergerius</hi> (hauing ben ſometimes Biſhop of <hi>Iuſtinopolis,</hi> and the Popes legate in <hi>Germany)</hi> by the writings of our men which hee had vndertaken to confute, was brought to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging of the truth, euen he confeſſed that hee found in <hi>Pole-land</hi> forty Churches eſtabliſhed in good order, by thoſe brethren which they neuer thought would come to paſſe, who had baniſhed them with ſo great cruelt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <p>Moreouer it cannot be denied, but that the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution in the Low-countries, furniſhed the domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Palatine</hi> Elector, with many teachers, and Preachers of the word, adorned with all kinde of good learning and knowledge; whoſe godly labours did greatly aduance the worke of reformation begun by <hi>Frederick</hi> the third Elector.</p>
            <p>The like alſo fell out in this countrey. For when as after the bleſſed deceaſe of that moſt worthy, pious and vertuous Prince, ſome alteration in Religion had driuen and diſperſed Miniſters of the word into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, by theſe miniſters in like manner, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the truth was propagated and ſpread into other places.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6504:11"/>
Furthermore by what meanes thinke we, that the moſt famous Dukedome of <hi>Wirtenberg</hi> was brought to the acknowledging of the Goſpell? was it not when the Duke <hi>Huldrick</hi> himſelfe was diſpoſſeſſed and caſt out of his Dukedome? for whereas hee liued priuately with <hi>Phillip</hi> the Landgraue of <hi>Haſsia,</hi> and there heard the teachers of the ſincere Religion prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, &amp; had before that beene preſent at a collogue and conference at <hi>Marpurge,</hi> his minde tooke ſuch a taſt of true Religion, as that after, hauing receiued his Dukedome, hee procured carefully the ſame true Religion to be preached vnto his ſubiects.</p>
            <p>Neither hath God vſed theſe meanes onely, for the propagation and aduancement of his word, but alſo many other courſes that haue beene maruellous.</p>
            <p>For I call <hi>Hungary</hi> to witneſſe, that euen Souldiers and men of Warre haue giuen furtherance to Gods word. For whereas the Dutch Army brought thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by King <hi>Ferdinandus,</hi> had in it many Lutheranes, by their meanes that Kingdome better diſcerned of Popiſh Idolatry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Italy</hi> alſo may teſtifie the like of it ſelfe, when both the Army of Charles the fifth beſieged the Pope, and ſome diſſentions began to growe betweene the Pope and the Venetians.</p>
            <p>To the number of theſe other meanes, I may alſo adde diuine and ſpirituall ſongs, which hauing beene made by Preachers of the Goſpell, and accuſtomed to be ſung by poore Schollers, inſinuated and cloſely conuaied the knowledge of the truth into an infinite number of men in <hi>Germany</hi> and the <hi>Low-countries,</hi> and chiefely in <hi>Hungary,</hi> where for the want of the Art of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6504:12"/>
Printing, this meanes was deuiſed, that the ſongs which had beene endited by the teachers, young boyes and ſchollers ſhould deuoutely and ſweetely ſing, not onely at mens doores, but euen at feaſts and banquets.</p>
            <p>Moreouer I thinke that I may truely ſay, that it hath beene a great meanes to further the knowledge of the trueth, that particular Schooles haue beene founded and erected in many places, and that diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations haue beene held by the profeſſors of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell with the Papiſts. Of which ſort are the diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions held at that time at <hi>Lipſwick</hi> in the yeare 1519, <note place="margin">1519.</note> at <hi>Zurich</hi> and <hi>Breſla</hi> 1523, at <hi>Baſile</hi> 1524, at <hi>Norimberge</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1523.</note> 1525, at <hi>Bathe</hi> in <hi>Switherland</hi> 1526, at <hi>Bern</hi> 1528, at <note place="margin">1524.</note> 
               <hi>London</hi> 1549, and ſuch like. <note place="margin">1525.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 Another likenes betweene this age and the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue <note place="margin">1526.</note> Church may bee in this, that the enemies of <note place="margin">1528.</note> the trueth ſet vpon the Chriſtians of the primitiue <note place="margin">1549.</note> Church, ſometimes with ſeueritie of edicts and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, after which grieuous puniſhments, and at the length by open warre: in the very like maner, for the ſpace of theſe hundred yeares, grieuous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations haue beene often publiſhed againſt true Religion and the profeſſors of it. And when they lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle preuailed, they killed infinite multitudes of men by fire and water, by the ſword and by hanging, and many other kinds of puniſhments: and when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe meanes had the like ſucceſſe which they deſired, they came at length to this, that ſtrong Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were leuied, and brought into <hi>Germany,</hi> the <hi>Low-countries,</hi> and into <hi>France,</hi> to haue rooted out true Religion, if it had beene poſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:6504:12"/>
Further alſo as in that time the heathen Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours (whether they would or no) heard the confeſſions and Apologies of the Chriſtian faith, which are extant and to be read in <hi>Iuſtin Martyr, Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoras, Tertullian,</hi> and others: Euen ſo in this our age, Kings and Keſars, haue of neceſſitie beene made to take notice and information of the trueth of the Goſpell, which in all things they did not approue of.</p>
            <p>For who is ignorant that the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth was preſent at the publicke reading of the confeſſion of <hi>Ausburge,</hi> ſo named of the Citie where this was done? Likewiſe to King <hi>Ferdinandus,</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their faith was both exhibited and read by the brethren and profeſſors in <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Morauia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We read likewiſe that <hi>Frauncis,</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> heard with his owne eares the famous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Chriſtians of <hi>Merindole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Theodore Beza,</hi> in the conference at <hi>Poeſſy,</hi> the King and the Queene, yea all <hi>Fraunce</hi> in a manner hearing it, deliuered the Articles of our faith, ſo ſoundly and ſo effectually, as that the Cardinall of <hi>Lorraine</hi> ſaide, that hee wiſhed that either <hi>Beza</hi> had beene dumbe, or that all the States there preſent had beene deafe that day.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Yet will we not ſtay heere, but obſerue another point of compariſon: for in the primitiue Church, there were very many Chriſtians who (as the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Hiſtory doth witneſſe) profeſſed the truth of the Goſpell with the loſſe of their goods, and alſo of their very life it ſelfe: So likewiſe in theſe hundred yeares laſt paſt, God hath ſet before our eyes notable and famous examples of Chriſtian conſtancy in an
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6504:13"/>
infinite number of moſt worthy perſons, men and women, rich and poore, learned and vnlearned, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vn-noble.</p>
            <p>The regard of the time will not ſuffer me heere to enlarge my ſelfe, yet can I not by any meanes paſſe by in ſilence, in <hi>Germany</hi> the houſes and the families of the Electors, to wit, that the houſe of <hi>Brandeburge, Saxony,</hi> and the <hi>Palatine</hi> haue brought forth thoſe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall perſons, to whom you may truely apply the ſpeach which by the Apoſtle is vttered of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that they eſteemed the reproach of Chriſt to be greater riches, then the treaſures of the <hi>Egyptians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt let vs goe to the houſe of <hi>Brandburge,</hi> and call to minde <hi>George</hi> the Marqueſſe of <hi>Brandenburge,</hi> who being then to King <hi>Lewis,</hi> the great Prefect and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of his Court, retained with his helpe, and defended with his aide, the Chriſtians in <hi>Sileſia, Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> being charged and burdned with diuers ſlaunders.</p>
            <p>After alſo, when the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, in the aſſembly at <hi>Ausburge,</hi> publiſhed a ſeuere edict and Proclamation, with a moſt grieuous puniſhment ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it, charging all men to abandon the Religion of the Goſpell, the ſaide Lord Marqueſſe, had this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable report of his conſtancy, that fearing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the Emperours indignation, hee boldly ſaide kneeling before his Maieſtie, that he had rather yeeld his head to be ſmitten and cut off, then to depart the leaſt iot from the truth, which he had once acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and receiued, which when hee once had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken openly, they ſay that the Emperour anſwered, that the cutting off his head was not ſought for.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:6504:13"/>
Will yee goe from <hi>Brandeburg</hi> to <hi>Saxonie?</hi> There we ſhall ſee Duke Henry the progenitour of the two moſt gratious Electors <hi>Mauricius</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily ſhewing how deepe rootes the loue of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell had taken in him.</p>
            <p>For when his brother <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> (who was a moſt earneſt defender of the Popiſh Religion) a litle before his death, hauing cauſed it to be ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him by meſſengers (ſent for that purpoſe) that hee would make him his heire, vpon condition, that he would forſake the Religion Euangelical reformed; but if he refuſed to performe the condition, that he would giue all his dominions to King <hi>Ferdinandus:</hi> Duke <hi>Henry</hi> of whom I ſpake, anſwering preſently, ſaide plainly and expreſly to him; this your meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage euidently repreſenteth and bringeth into my minde that which is written in the holy Scriptures, when Sathan promiſed to Chriſt, the Kingdomes of the whole world, vpon condition, that falling downe at his feete, hee would worſhip and adore him. Doe you thinke that I eſteeme any worldly riches and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit more, then I doe the glory of God? Certainely your expectation doeth much deceiue you. With which anſwere hee diſmiſſed thoſe meſſengers, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his former ſpeach, this notable ſentence, that hee had rather bee poore with Chriſt, then rich with the Pope.</p>
            <p>Which memorable act of his religious pietie wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not his reward from God. For before that the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates and meſſengers had returned ſome, Duke <hi>Georg</hi> his brother dying, without executing that his deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, altogether againſt his will, left Duke <hi>Henry</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:6504:14"/>
his heire and ſucceſſor. And what ſhould I ſpeake of <hi>Iohn Frederick Elector</hi> of famous memory? Of whom, the Emperour <hi>Ferdinandus</hi> himſelfe is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to haue ſaid to Doctor <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>vius</hi> chiefe Phiſitian of the Elector of <hi>Saxony:</hi> that <hi>Iohn Frederick</hi> Flector, was a Prince of a magnanimous and high courage, whoſe valour and vertue if his Souldiers had followed in the Warre, with like animoſitie and bouldneſſe, hee had neuer beene ouercome. Further hee is reported to haue ſaid, that hee ſtood by the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> and beheld with how chearefull and gratious a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance hee came to the Emperour, preſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, not as a captiue and priſoner, but chearefull as one that ſhould haue led a daunce.</p>
            <p>And ſurely that he excelled in the greatneſſe of an inuincible minde and courage, he made it manifeſt in his very impriſonment and captiuitie, to the wonder and admiration of all men.</p>
            <p>For in the aſſembly at <hi>Ausburge,</hi> the Emperour had drawen all the States of the Empire to his purpoſe, that ſtricken with feare, they freely profeſſed, that they would receiue whatſoeuer the Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell that was to be called, ſhould determine of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Then he required and commaunded the Prince being priſoner to doe the like. But he then anſwered that in all other things he was ready with all ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to yeeld his ſeruice and obedience: but in that which concerned Religion and conſcience, hee hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be fought him in his gracious clemency to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect him.</p>
            <p>So great was the magnanimitie of this Prince E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector when he was a priſoner, ſo great was his zeale
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6504:14"/>
for the true worſhip of God, when the other States being yet free, and yet affrighted with the feares of daungers, profeſſed that they would willingly obey the decree of the counſell that was to be held: whoſe iudgement was yet vnknowen what it would bee. Therefore <hi>Melanchthon</hi> a moſt religious Diuine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably in verſe commended the conſtancy, of this like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moſt religious Prince and Elector, ſaying.</p>
            <q>He won more praiſe by conſtant profeſsion of faith, then if he at home had fought fierce and terrible battels.</q>
            <p>Furthermore the County <hi>Palatine,</hi> is able to ſhew alſo in this glorious field, and to this day commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to all poſteritie, thoſe moſt famous Princes, <hi>Otto, Henry,</hi> and <hi>Frederick</hi> the third of that name, either of them Electors, and moſt conſtant defenders of the trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ottho Henricus</hi> deſired rather to looſe the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palitie of <hi>Neuburg,</hi> then by forſaking the truth of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to keepe it, and to win the fauour of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and of the Pope: which faithfulnes and conſtancy in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, God recompenced with a large &amp; ample bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. For he not onely reſtored vnto him, the foreſaid dominion; but alſo, <hi>Frederick</hi> the ſecond being dead, he gloriouſly aduanced him to the Electorſhip.</p>
            <p>Behold alſo the Count <hi>Palatine Frederick</hi> the third, him to whom pietie it ſelfe gaue his Sir-name, ſo that he was renowned &amp; called <hi>Fredericus Pious,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with me a little his diuers and great trials which he endured for the cauſe of Religion.</p>
            <p>He was conſtrained, ſometimes to auoide the darts of his brother, ſometimes to withſtand his children, and ſometimes to reſiſt his kinſ-folke, yea at the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6504:15"/>
length in the aſſembly at <hi>Ausborow</hi> he had the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour himſelfe and the Princes and States of the ſacred Empire greateſt aduerſaries vnto him.</p>
            <p>Yet ſurely <hi>Caeſars</hi> Maieſtie notably made anſwere for him to the Electors and Princes that would haue excluded and ſhut out the ſaide <hi>Frederick Pius,</hi> out of the peace of the Empire, ſaying, I muſt anſwere you, as Chriſt did <hi>Salome:</hi> you knowe not what you aske. Doe you not know, that he is a Prince of the Empire? will you be at diſcord among your ſelues? Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſame Emperour, very ſeuerely and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily commaunded the ſame Elector <hi>Frederick,</hi> to change and vtterly forſake his Religion, which was ſaid to be a diuers Religion from that which was ſaid to be allowed at <hi>Ausburge,</hi> and infected (as they ſaid) with the error of Caluiniſme. Then the Elector o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly and plainly (as the loue of Religion perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him) to this effect declared his minde to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Maieſtie, that in the matter of Faith and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, hee did acknowledge one onely Lord, to wit, God, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</p>
            <p>That ſuch queſtion and buſineſſe concerned not the loſſe of any temporal eſtate, or of this preſent life, but the euerlaſting ſaluation of the ſoule: which as he had receiued and had it recommended vnto him from Chriſt his Lord and Sauiour: ſo he both ought and would keepe it entire and whole without hurt or blemiſh vnto him, euen with the daunger and loſſe of this preſent life. Furthermore he ſaid, that hee was willing and ready to yeelde to any whatſoeuer they were, a iuſt reaſon, apologie, and defence of his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme and Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:6504:15"/>
Which magnanimitie and courage of a conſtant faith, <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> and Elector admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, friendly and brotherly ſtriking with his open hand the ſhoulder of this moſt pious Prince <hi>Frederick,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Frederick,</hi> thou doeſt farre excell vs all in pietie and Religion.</p>
            <p>Behold a chearefull minde of a Prince in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth, nobly reſembling the Emperour <hi>Iouinian,</hi> who being taken by the Souldiers to receiue the Imperiall dignitie, refuſed to take it vpon him, except the Army by whom hee was choſen, would caſt away their Idols, and embrace the ſinceritie of Chriſtian Faith.</p>
            <p>Our owne Prince alſo, in like manner a moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant profeſſor of Religion, reſolued rather to looſe the dignitie to be one of the ſeauen Electors, then to abandon the truth of the Goſpell, if hee could not keepe his Electorſhip without the loſſe of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>Now let vs proceede from <hi>Germany</hi> to <hi>Italy,</hi> and bring out before you, two worthy champions for the faith, out of the Kingdome of <hi>Naples,</hi> to wit, <hi>Galeaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Caracciolus</hi> Vice-Marques, and the ſame a ſonne of the ſiſter of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth; the other <hi>Iohn Berniardin Boniface</hi> Marques of <hi>Oria.</hi> Both theſe were enflamed with ſo great a zeale of Religion, as that all their worldly dignities neglected, and the honour of their life and ſtate deſpiſed, they forſooke their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and their countrey, and led the reſt of their mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall liues in ſuch a voluntary baniſhment, as the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Religion laid vpon them.</p>
            <p>Heere alſo I could name you many other worthy
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6504:16"/>
and famous perſonages in <hi>Spaine, Italy, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Germanie,</hi> which ſome of them ſecretly, and ſome of them by open violence ſuffred death for the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpell. But the Martirologies and ſtories of the Martyrs haue caſed mee of that burden of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſing them, (as being ſet out purpoſely to declare and to regiſter the names of theſe who haue borne witneſſe to the truth) and may be repaired and reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto for this matter.</p>
            <p>Yet cannot I in ſilence paſſe by any meanes, that onely in <hi>Belgia</hi> (containing the 17 prouinces of the <hi>Low-countries)</hi> whiles <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth yet liued, were ſlaine and murdered fiftie thouſand Chriſtians, and that the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> cruelly boaſted, that in the ſpace of ſix yeares after hee had beene gouernour of that countrey eighteene thouſand perſons had ben killed by his commaundement, and alſo from the yeare 1576, to the agreement at <hi>Gaunt</hi> there had pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the tiranny of the Papiſts thirtie thouſand.</p>
            <p>Yet there was a greater Vintage and Harueſt in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> for it may be proued by arguments worthy to be belieued, that from the yeare 1564, to the yeare <note place="margin">1564.</note> 1586, that is in the ſpace of two and twentie yeares, that one hundred and forty thouſand godly perſons ſealed and ſigned with their blood the ſinceritie of Religion. Which is ſo reckoned, as that, they are not numbred in this account, who vnder <hi>Henry</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>Frauncis</hi> the firſt, being roaſted and burnt, went vp to the fire with ſo great courage and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of minde, and ſo to the death gaue teſtimony to the truth, as that in the yeare 1533, the tongues of the Martirs were cut out, that they might not be able to ſpeake vnto the people.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:6504:16"/>
Now in <hi>England</hi> it is incredible to be ſpoken, what ſlaughter and how many dead corpes haue beene made: how many excellent men (amongſt whom ſome were Biſhops &amp; Arch-biſhops) in the Raigne of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> being burnt aliue with fire, without feare endured that ſhamefull and cruell death with maruellous ſtrength and power of Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>And if wee ſhould alſo declare the notable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible conſtancy of <hi>Rochell</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and of <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denborowe</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> heere wee ſhould haue a large field to diſcourſe, to their immortall praiſe. But wee are to proceed, and make another new compariſon betweene the auntienter Apoſtolick, and latter refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2 In theſe times the Chriſtians being miſerably af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, God (appearing and ſhining through theſe cloudes vnto them) then at length gloriouſly lifted vp, and exalted his Church, when it lay caſt downe to the loweſt, &amp; was euen troden vnderfoote. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Sulpitius Seuerus</hi> was bould to ſay, writing of the ten yeares perſecution vnder the Emperours <hi>Diocleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>Maximinian,</hi> wee neuer conquered with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory and triumph, then when wee could not bee conquered with the continuall ſlaughters and maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres of ten yeares together: In like maner, in theſe hundred yeares laſt paſt, beſides and aboue the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, opinion and thoughts of all men, God often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times mightely deliuered his Church, taking it, as it were out of the very iawes of the enemies.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1521, after the departure of <hi>Luther,</hi> who in the aſſemblies of the States of the Empire at <hi>Wornis</hi> had appeared and preſented himſelfe before
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6504:17"/>
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> and the Princes of the Empire, to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for his proceedings, there was ſet and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed an edict or proclamation of moſt ſharpe ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie againſt the profeſſors of the Goſpell, whereof the Popes Legat, Cardinall <hi>Ierome Alexander</hi> is reported to haue ſaide to <hi>Marinus Caracciolus;</hi> Oh, my <hi>Caracci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olus,</hi> if we haue done nothing elſe at this diet and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, yet this we haue effected (as I am in good hope) that by this edict and mandate of <hi>Caeſars</hi> wee ſhall ſhortly ſee the <hi>Germans</hi> at warre one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and tumbling in their owne blood.</p>
            <p>But what fell out? a little after, there aroſe an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great trouble in <hi>Spaine:</hi> ſo as the Emperour went thither to pacifie it, and the profeſſors of the Goſpell had a litle breathing time, as ſome milder aire appearing. For the Imperiall edict being mittigated and qualified by the States of the Empire aſſembled at <hi>Norinberg,</hi> the true doctrine was ſeene daily to bee more largely and more couragiouſly ſpread and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1526, and the fourteenth of <hi>Ianuary, Charles</hi> the fift being Emperour, and <hi>Frauncis</hi> the firſt being King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> with great coniunction and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of minde and affections endeauoured and went about it, ioyning their forces together, to pull vp by the rootes the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Religon (as they call it) but altogether in vaine. For the Pope himſelfe brake the bond and league, making the Emperour ſo much buſines in <hi>Italy,</hi> that hee profeſſed by publicke writing, that the Pope was in all the fault, that he had hitherto with leſſe ſucceſſe ſuppreſſed the hereſie (as he termed it) of the Lutherans.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:6504:17"/>
Againe in the yeare 1530. did not all men feare and tremble at the publiſhing of that moſt cruell edict of the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> wherewith at the Dyet at <hi>Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> hee thundred againſt the profeſſors of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell? but behold, God, as from heauen, deliuered them. For the Turke, (as one that had beene drawen thither by the haire of his head) came into <hi>Auſtria:</hi> which rumour cauſed the Emperour not vnwillingly to grant peace to the Proteſtants, that hee might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine aide of them againſt the Turke, the common e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of all Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe, the league agreed vpon at <hi>Smale-cald,</hi> being broken, &amp; proſperous ſucceſſe making all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto <hi>Caeſars</hi> power, who knoweth not that which hapned. For when it was thought, that the cauſe of reformation had now beene vtterly ouerthrowen in <hi>Germanie,</hi> Almightie God fully ouercame and ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Conquerers minde, and ſo perplexed him, that he not onely no more vrged the Generall Councell (to whoſe determination the States of the Empire had before promiſed to yeeld all obedience) but alſo made an vnneceſſary and needles warre with the Pope, and deſpaired of ſucceſſe in fighting any more with the Germanes, who yet before, he ſuppoſed to haue bin wholly conquered and ſubdued.</p>
            <p>Neither was it otherwiſe with the <hi>Heluetians,</hi> who being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to defend with Armes the libertie of the Euangellicall profeſſion, were once or twiſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by papiſts: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the truth trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth as inuincible their Churches, euen to this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>England</hi> alſo may be a witneſſe hereof, wherein men almoſt deſpaired of the maintainers of the Goſpell,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6504:18"/>
when as by the raigne of Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> many goodly lights had beene extinguiſhed, and ſo many ſtrong buttreſſes and pillars had beene ouerthrowen &amp; caſt downe to the ground.</p>
            <p>But the Lord, who calleth light out of darkenes, he called that moſt gratious Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> out of the priſon, &amp; placed her in the royall throne of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whereby all the hope of the Papiſt was diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and expoſed to ſhame and ignominie.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Fraunce</hi> will teſtifie this, which was moſt ſhamefully defiled and ſtained with that horrible maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre and ſlaughter that was made of true profeſſors in the yeare 1572. For at that time there was celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and kept at <hi>Rome</hi> a ſolemne thanks-giuing to God for that action performed with ſo great ſucceſſe, &amp; ſo agreeably to their deſire, in the rooting out of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonets, (as they called the profeſſors of the trueth of the Goſpell.)</p>
            <p>But within a yeare after, the multitude of profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors appeared in ſo great number, as a man would haue thought that all thoſe had beene riſen from the dead, and reſtored to life againe.</p>
            <p>Neither are there wanting like examples in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary, Bohemia, Morauia, Sileſia, Auſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ria.</hi> For about ſome thirteene yeares agone, theſe aduerſaries with very great endeauours deſired to cut off all meanes of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing the Religion reformed. But vtterly in vaine, God withſtanding them; who ſending them his helpe from heauen, brought the matter to that paſſe, that greater libertie was granted to theſe countries then they euer enioyed in any time before.</p>
            <p>Finally, for the laſt point of this compariſon: In the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6504:18"/>
primitiue Church God by manifeſt ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens ſhewed the ſeueritie of his iuſt iudgement vpon many tirants and perſecutors of the Church, by their fearfull ends and tragicall deaths.</p>
            <p>In like maner <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperour 200. yeares agone hauing burnt at <hi>Conſtance, Iohn Huſſe,</hi> a moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and godly Preacher, together with him burnt and conſumed all his owne royall eſtate. For decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing without heire male, <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> his Grand-ſonne by his daughter ſucceeded him, and ſo hee confined the celebritie and honour of his name in the ſpace of a fewe yeares. So likewiſe in this laſt age wee haue receiued by report, and ſeene with our eyes that ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance hath followed them at their heeles, which bearing impietie and vngodlineſſe in their hearts, and ſhewing it openly by ſtrange crueltie, went about with all their power to aſſaile and to plucke vp by the rootes the pure doctrine of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1546. <hi>George Wiſehart</hi> a Preacher of the Goſpell in <hi>Scotland</hi> (after burnt to aſhes by the commaundement of Cardinall <hi>Beton)</hi> in the midſt of the flames of fire prophetically foretold the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of the death and ouerthrow that hung ouer his head. And that not in vaine, for hee was killed that very yeare, and that ſo, as in the ſame place, where the ſtake and aſhes of that conſtant Martyr had beene ſeene not long before, in the ſame place ſo ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the dead body of that tyrant was to be ſeene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the hate and ſcorne of all men.</p>
            <p>With him reckon alſo <hi>Steuen Gardner,</hi> who being Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and Cancelor to Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> emploied his ſeruice &amp; power very buſily to deſtroy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6504:19"/>
the Chriſtians. But his puniſhment followed not long after: for being taken with a ſore diſeaſe, and deſpairing of the fauour and mercy of God, he cried out, alaſle for me, I haue ſinned with <hi>Peter,</hi> but I haue not wept, nor ſeriouſly &amp; truly repented as <hi>Peter</hi> did.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Fraunce,</hi> remember <hi>Minerius,</hi> making war with the innocent men of <hi>Merindoll,</hi> and miſerably killing and murthering them with more then <hi>Scythian</hi> and <hi>Barbarian</hi> cruelty. What? art thou ſorry? and doeſt thou ſigh and lament to heare it? ſtay a while, and thou ſhalt ſee and acknowledge the wonderfull iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vengeance of God vpon him. For this ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <hi>Minerius</hi> falling into a moſt grieuous and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſickneſſe, ended his vngodly life, with horrible crying and howling.</p>
            <p>Kings alſo furniſh vs with ſome examples of tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ends. For <hi>Fruancis,</hi> the firſt king of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> in the agony of death, felt how heauily the blood of the <hi>Wald<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſes</hi> and <hi>Merindolians</hi> lay vpon his conſcience, wherefore hee gaue commandement and charge to his ſonne <hi>Henry</hi> that hee ſhould put to death <hi>Iohn Monke,</hi> by whoſe counſell and perſwaſion he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun the perſecution: which <hi>Monke</hi> perceiuing, ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily fled, and ſo eſcaped the preſent danger.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe we haue heard that <hi>Henry</hi> the 2. King of <hi>France,</hi> hauing often threatned, and ſaid, that with his own eies he would ſee <hi>Burges</hi> to be conſumed &amp; burnt with fire vpon a wound taken in the eye in his run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at-Tilt, ended his life with very great torments.</p>
            <p>Neither was the end of <hi>Frauncis</hi> the ſecond of that name any better, who hauing denied the Chriſtians free exerciſe of the Religion of the Goſpell: (who by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6504:19"/>
ſupplication had requeſted it) hee alſo by an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume riſen in his braine, and running at his eare, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his eare putrified and rotten.</p>
            <p>And thou alſo <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> goe thou alſo and defile thy hands with the blood of thy ſubiects. Thou alſo didſt miſerably periſh in thine owne blood. And you two tirants (I ſpeake of <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe)</hi> doe you alſo take paines in the hainous crime of the maſſacre and ſlaughter at <hi>Paris;</hi> doe you alſo kill, murder and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy: but with what ſucceſſe, euen, and iſſue haue you done it? either of you ended your life, with a violent and bloody death, but the reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you haue not driuen out of <hi>Fraunce.</hi> But what doe I ſpeake of theſe things, the Emperour himſelfe, <hi>Charles</hi> the fiſt, hee confeſſed that hee had vſed and emploied all his force and power, to eſtabliſh the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Pope, and to maintaine his dignity, but that his endeauour had beene all in vaine, &amp; that his mony and treaſure was ſpent, which loſſe was tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and might be borne, but that which was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether intollerable, he had loſt his honourable name amongſt men, and his eſtimation &amp; dignitie, the loſſe whereof was not to be recouered by any meanes.</p>
            <p>Heere it were worth our labour to note &amp; marke the perfidious falling away of Apoſtatates, and the infirmity of the faithfull. Heere alſo inteſtine and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſſenſions and diſcords were to bee touched, and to be compared with the contentions of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and primitiue Church: but the regard of this preſent time doth not ſuffer me ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>Therefore, let it ſuffice to haue heard, that Chriſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6504:20"/>
the Lord hath moſt effectually expreſſed, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed really, and in powerfull act and deede, the name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> and <hi>Sauiour,</hi> that was giuen him by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from God, in that hee doth ſo fatherly gather, ſo wiſely gouerne, ſo mightely preſerue, and ſo iuſtly protect his Church againſt all the aduerſaries and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of it.</p>
            <p>Now let the Ieſuits goe, and vain-gloriouſly boaſt of the miracles, which they ſay, haue beene done in the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indiaes:</hi> but wee moſt worthily publiſh and magnifie the miracles, iuſtly to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red &amp; wondred at, which God hath done in our own dayes, and in the age of our fathers, in <hi>Germany, Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Spaine, Italy, Fraunce, Hungary, Bohemia, Pole-land, Denmark</hi> and <hi>Swed land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For theſe are indeed that which they are ſaid to be, miracles.</p>
            <p>That God hath wrought ſo great things by ſo meane and baſe inſtruments.</p>
            <p>That the doctrine of the Goſpell within ſo fewe yeares, hath like the lightning, enlightned ſo many countries and Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>That by meanes altogether contrary to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of man, the ſinceritie and puritie of the doctrine of the Goſpell flouriſheth at this day, being propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſpread faire and neare.</p>
            <p>That by how much the greater the crueltie of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants hath beene in blood ſheding, in burning &amp; han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the godly, ſo much the further hath the ſound of the Goſpell bin heard, &amp; paſſed into more places.</p>
            <p>That a moſt puiſſant and mighty Emperour, going through <hi>Germany</hi> with ſuch ſucceſſe of many victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6504:20"/>
as he could haue wiſhed, yet was notable by any meanes to conquer &amp; ſubdue the Goſpell in <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That in <hi>Fraunce</hi> ſix Kings continually ſucceeding one another, and employing all their forces, and vſing many and diuers meanes and practiſes for it, yet haue not beene able to effect the ſuppreſſion of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches in <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, the greateſt King that hath beene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> hath waſted all the treaſure which he had gathered in the Eaſt, and in the Weſt, for the roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of Religion, partly in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and partly in <hi>England,</hi> and chiefely in the <hi>Low countries,</hi> and that with no other euent and ſucceſſe, but that theſe huge maſſes of treaſure being exhauſted and loſt, and his Kingdome being caſt into many great ſtraits and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties of debt, before his death full ſore againſt his will, he heard this meſſage deliuered to him, that the reformed Churches in <hi>France, England,</hi> and the <hi>Low-countri<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> did proſper and flouriſh, as they had done in any former time.</p>
            <p>Which things being ſo, worthily doe we all extoll and magnifie this moſt gracious goodnes and mercy of our God, who in goodnes add power excelleth all, whereby when we were drowned in the midſt of a ſea of errors and darkeneſſe in Popery, hath illuminated and enlightned vs with the moſt clear &amp; goodly light of the knowledge of himſelfe, and of his Goſpell.</p>
            <p>For if in the old Teſtament the godly ſo often ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated and praiſed with ſongs, the redemption of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and from their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Madian,</hi> ſurely we haue far greater cauſe, why wee ſhould magnifie with all praiſe and honour our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6504:21"/>
maruellous deliuerances from the Idolatry of Anti-chriſt.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, this hiſtoricall commemoration and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſall of the admirable &amp; wonderfull worke which we haue heard, to haue beene performed by God in his Church, ought to giue encouragement to all the faithfull with greater alacritie and chearfulneſſe, and with greater ſtrength and conſtancy to keepe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the truth which they haue once acknowledged: which being grounded and founded ſtedfaſtly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely in the holy Scripture, hath beene againe and newly confirmed in theſe laſt hundred yeares by ſo ſingular and excellent miracles.</p>
            <p>And this we ought the rather to doe, becauſe wee knowe that our Sauiour Ieſus doth ſtill liue, and wee are certainly perſwaded, that as he hath done hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſo likewiſe alwayes hereafter, hee will gather, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, and preſerue his Church.</p>
            <p>Now let vs alſo remember that it is our part and dutie to worſhip and honour this Ieſus our Sauiour with our mouth, with our hearts, and with all our ſtrength. For he it is (as the Angell expreſly teſtifieth) which will ſaue and preſerue his people. Of which people they onely are to bee accompted, who doe not walke, nor liue according to the fleſh, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Spirit: whereof, who ſeeth not this to follow? That he that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, is none of his: and that he who is none of Chriſts, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in any ſort enioy the comfort of this name of a Sauiour?</p>
            <p>Let vs then embrace our moſt faithfull Sauiour, let vs loue him, let vs feare him, and let vs honour
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6504:21"/>
him: So without all doubt, we ſhall prooue by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that he wil renew againe hereafter, vnto vs his auncient fauour, and will moſt mightely protect vs his Chriſtian Church, by his patronage and defence from all our enemies both of ſoule and body.</p>
            <p>For this ſaith Amen, that is, that true and faithfull witneſſe, the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt my Church.</p>
            <p>To this mighty and great Sauiour, be thankes, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory, for all the comfort, helpe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits hitherto beſtowed vpon vs, both now, and in all ages, for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>THE PRAYER.</head>
               <p>MOſt Gracious God, and mercifull father, we giue thee thankes for all thy benefits, wherewith hitherto, thou haſt largely and bountefully bleſſed vs. O Lord my God, thy thoughts are great and thy workes admirable and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, which thou ſetteſt before vs, to behold and conſider. Nothing can, nor ought to be compared vnto thee. I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare thy workes, and ſpeake of them, although they exceed all account and number. Wee acknowledge it to proceede from thy grace and fauour, that in all places thou haſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly gathered a people that is pleaſing and acceptable vnto thee; that thou haſt wiſely gouerned, and mightily preſerued the ſame. Eſpecially wee praiſe thee that it hath pleaſed thee, to call vs in theſe countries to the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, and that this day thou haſt graunted thy grace to vs ſitting by the cratch of thy new
<pb facs="tcp:6504:22"/>
borne Sonne, to heare how ſweet<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly the Angels ſung their heau<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nly hymne and ſong; and how ioyfully they greeted and congratulated vs, for the exceeding great benefit of thy Sonne ſent to take our fleſh and nature vpon him. And not onely to heare this, but moreouer alſo to ſee how the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards did adore him; <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Anna</hi> bleſſed him: the wiſe men that came to him from the Eaſt, did honour him with gold, myrrh and frankincenſe. Bleſſed bee thy holy name for euermore, for theſe and all other benefits, which thou doeſt beſtow vpon vp, and wherwith thou doeſt adorne vs. Gracious God and mercifull Father, we beſeech thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for the time to come, to ſhew forth thy maruellous workes amongſt vs, and alwayes to gather a Church to thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, and graciouſly to preſerue this which thou haſt already gathered, that the number of them may daily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, who may truly acknowledge thee and thy Sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and may celebrate and magnifie thee, both in this life, and alſo in that which is to come for euermore.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, with earneſt prayers wee beſeech thee, as thou haſt done hitherto, ſo likewiſe hereafter graciouſly and mercifully to turne away from vs, the fury of warre, the ſcarcitie and dearth of victuals, and the plague of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, and whatſoeuer beſides may bee hurtfull to our countries.</p>
               <p>Driue away alſo farre from vs the moſt ſauage crueltie of the Pope, and of his adhaerents, hinder and reſtraine his counſels that they take not effect.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe we b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeech thee to grace and adorne with all maner of bleſsings, the Emperours Maieſty, the Royall dignitie of the King of great Britaine, as alſo all other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings, the Electors of the Empire and other Princes, eſpecially t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e moſt illuſtrious and gratious Prince <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6504:22"/>
                  <hi>Count-Palatine</hi> Elector our gratious Lord, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the moſt illuſtrious Princeſſe his wife, and the Princeſſe daughter of the late Elector: and our young Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and all the noble houſe of the <hi>Counts-Palatines,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Electors, with their Counſellors and Officers, maintaine and preſerue them all with thy gracious patronage, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and defence.</p>
               <p>Take care alſo, we beſeech thee, of all Widowes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes, and preſerue our bodies with the comfort of health, and crowne our life with Chriſtian vprightneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie.</p>
               <p>Helpe all thoſe which endure diuers afflictions, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as ſuffer grieuous perſecutions for the truths ſake. Make them knowe by their experience, that Ieſus our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our is more able to comfort them, then all the world to make them to ſorrow.</p>
               <p>Finally, when the ſhort terme and time of our life ſhall paſſe away, refreſh and comfort vs before wee depart from hence: and receiuing vs into the armes of thy mercy, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate vs out of this old world, to that new one, which is not finiſhed nor ended with any courſe of the Sunne, or of the Moone: but wherein thy ſelfe art to bee the Sunne, the Moone, and all in all things, theſe mercies we aske in the name of Ieſus Christ, and pray alſo further as he hath taught vs. Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:6504:23"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg 3. helpeth, r. <hi>fulfileth.</hi> p. 4. adorned r. <hi>adored.</hi> p. 17. Treptquine. r. <hi>Trepto.</hi> were, r <hi>was.</hi> p. 20. r. <hi>the Smalcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian warre.</hi> p. 22. r. <hi>with.</hi> for which. p. 24. <hi>retained</hi> for relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. p. 25. him, r. <hi>them</hi> ibid. ſome. r. <hi>home.</hi> p. 52. l. 2. r. <hi>there was ſet out &amp;c.</hi> p. 33. r. <hi>in their Churches.</hi> p. 39. adde. for <hi>and.</hi> pag, <hi>vltima,</hi> daughter read <hi>Dowager.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6504:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
